Hi, I'm Dr. Michael
Cherzella, and this is
the pre-lab lecture
for Still Technique,
Cervical, Lumbar, Thoracic,
Indominate, and Ribs.
Before going over the
material for this lab,
and especially before
coming to the actual lab,
please make sure you
review the material in
the Introduction to
Still Technique lecture.
In that lecture, you're
going to learn about a brief
history of the Still Technique,
you'll learn its basic
principles, as well as the
indications and contraindications
for the technique.
There's also a sample case
where you can see how you can
apply the still technique.
These are the session
objectives for the lab.
Essentially, by the end of
the lab, you'll be able to
perform the still technique
to the various regions
that we're going to list on
the next slide. You'll also
be able to perform the review
material from Foundation
Divacitopathic Medicine
Labs No. 7 and Labs No. 12.
This lecture specifically
will go over a
case so that by the
end of this you'll also
be able to understand
how to integrate the
still techniques into
a clinical scenario.
The new techniques we're
going to learn in this
lab are the still technique
for the OA, the AA,
C2 through C7, RIV1
inhalation and exhalation
dysfunctions. We're
going to learn that
in the seated position.
There are other
versions, but we're doing
the seated position.
Also,
a still technique for
the thoracic and lumbar
regions. They're the same
technique, except you
localize to a lower level
when you're in the lumbar.
And also, the still
technique for the
anteriorly and posteriorly
rotated innominates.
These new techniques
are described in
the handout and in
the posted lab videos.
We're not going to be going
over how to perform the
techniques in this lecture
what we're going to do here
is discuss a clinical scenario
which you can apply in
which you can apply many of
the techniques you're going
to learn so a 40 year old
man presents to your office
complaining of neck and back
pain after being involved
in a motor vehicle crash
two weeks ago he initially
felt fine after the accident
but was taken to the
emergency department where he
where they did cervical spine
and lumbosacral spine x
-rays and they were negative
A few days later, he
noticed pain in his neck,
upper back, and lower
back. The neck pain
and upper back pain
are sharp, bilateral,
and worse when he turns
his head to the left.
The pain is non-radiating.
He has no associated
numbness, tingling, or
weakness in his arms or hands.
The neck pain is 7 out
of 10 in severity. The
upper back pain is 5
out of 10 in severity.
The lower back pain is
bilateral, constant,
worse on the right, and
better with flexion.
It is worse with extension.
He has no radiation
of the pain and no
associated numbness,
tingling, weakness,
or bowel or bladder
function changes.
For his past medical
history, he has seasonal
allergies. He has
no surgical history.
He's only taking loratadine
10 milligrams daily.
His social history is
negative for the use
of drugs, alcohol,
tobacco, or caffeine.
He used to run three
miles a day, but he has
been unable to do that
since the accident.
His family history
is significant, only
that his mother had an
MI at the age of 67.
On physical exam, his
vitals are normal.
His upper and lower
extremity motor are normal.
His C567, L4, and S1 deep
tendon reflexes are normal.
He has no gross sensory
deficit in the upper or lower
extremities. There's a
negative Sperling's maneuver,
negative straight leg
raise bilaterally, and a
negative costovertebral
angle tenderness bilateral.
He has good radial and
pedal pulses bilaterally.
There's decreased gross
cervical range of motion
to extension, rotation
left, and side bending left.
You note bilateral hypertonic
sternocleidomastoid muscles.
as well as bilateral
cervical paravertebral
muscle spasm.
You note increased skin
drag and a positive
red reflex test over
T1 and T5 on the right.
There's paravertebral muscle
spasm from T1 to
T5 on the right.
There's a decreased
translation of
T12 and L1 region
from right to left.
There's bilateral
lumbar paravertebral
muscle spasm in the
entire lumbar spine.
There's also bilateral
psoas hypertonicity.
And while we're talking
about screening with
the positive red reflex
and the skin drag test,
when you're just scanning
the spine, you're
also looking for
viscerosomatic reflexes. In
this case, we're not
really noticing those.
But in general, whenever
you're diagnosing someone,
you should be scanning their
back and seeing if there's
anything. For instance,
you may find viscerosomatic
reflexes in T1 to T4
region on the left if a
patient's having some sort of
cardiac issues or bilaterally
from T1 to T5 or T1 to T6
depending on the source
you use for the lungs. for
the stomach t5 to t9 on
the on the left you may
find the similar findings
in the in the t9 region or
so for the gallbladder you
can keep going down and
into the colon as well so
you can go back and review
that material but it's
important to keep that in
mind whenever you're examining
someone's back that was
just a little aside there.
And then once you did
your screening type of
exams, then you look for
the more specific somatic
dysfunctions. And this
patient has OA, extended
side bend left, rotated
right, AA, rotated right,
C2, ERS right, C7, ERS right,
bilateral rib one, exhaled,
T1, ERS right, T5
ERS right, bilateral
respiratory diaphragm
hypertonicity, L1 ERS left,
there's a right on right
forward sacral torsion,
and there's a right
posteriorly rotated enominant.
So what's your assessment?
Well, there's looks like
there's been a whiplash
injury, there's neck pain,
cervicalgia, low back
pain, muscle spasm, and
multiple smack dysfunctions.
So what do we want to
do? What's the plan?
Well, for the
whiplash, neck pain,
you can do ice, heat
as needed. You can give
some cervical range
of motion stretches,
teach the patient
proper ergonomics, like
for sitting or for
working at a computer.
You might want to
consider physical
therapy if there's
no improvement.
You'll tell the
patient to modify the
sleeping position to
keep the neck relaxed.
And for any of the
pain, you can have the
patient take some ibuprofen
or Tylenol as needed.
For the low back
pain, you can have the
patient do some
stretches for the psoas.
Instruct the patient
not to sit more
than 45 minutes
without taking a break.
and also he can exercise
as tolerated go back to the
running but start slowly
and build back up so when
he's able to he can start
doing it i wouldn't push
it but you want him to
get out there and start
moving again also when he
sleeps if he sleeps on his
side maybe tell him to put
a pillow between his knees
that helps take some of
the stress off the low back
and for the smack dysfunctions
you're going to tell
him to do the omt as
described in the following
slides you'll also have him
drink plenty of water and
tell him he may feel sore
in the next day or two.
Every time you treat
someone with OMT, you should
inform them that they
may feel sore in the next
day or two. It's more
of an exercise soreness.
And again, make sure they
drink plenty of water.
It's also good to talk about
proper sleep hygiene in
case the patient isn't
getting enough sleep. Sleeping
a good seven and a half
to eight and a half hours
a night is much better
than sleeping four four or
five hours a night so how
are we going to approach
treating this patient with
OMT there are different
ways to do it some people
will look for the area of
greatest restriction and go
there and treat there and
then move out from those
areas that's a very good
approach in this case some
of those areas might be a
little a little um tight
and still a little really
aggravated so i might want
to try to go start from the
outside and move in a little
bit so the the way i'm
suggesting here is to start
at the legs treat the legs
look at them there's probably
other dysfunctions than
what i just listed earlier
you know there there might
be a spasm in the hamstrings
the hip adductors and the
abductors, the fibula head,
depending on where the,
you know, how the patient
was sitting and if they were
driving, if their foot was
on the brake and they were
jamming the brake and
then there was, the crash
occurred, there may be
dysfunctions in there. So you might
want to treat the legs
first, then move up, treat
the psoazes, and you could
do those, you could treat
those with muscle energy or
balanced segmentus tension.
Then move up to the lumbar
spine treat that l1 ers left
and you can use still
technique since we're talking
about this is still technique
lab you can use muscle
energy bouncing mentis tension
you might be able to use
hvla if the patient is
can tolerate that a little
counter strain treat the
posterior and nominate and now
again if the patient was was
driving with um with their
foot on the brake when the
accident occurred. Maybe
that femur could have driven
the inominate posterior.
That could be why there's
a posterior inominate. You
can do the still technique
for that. If it's really
jammed up, maybe do a
little bounce ligamentous
tension, muscle energy, and
then do still technique.
Then you can go and
treat that sacrum.
If it's still there, sometimes
treating the lumbar
and the inominates
will help to get rid of
that sacral dysfunction.
But if there is a sacral
dysfunction, there,
muscle energy or BLT. Now,
sometimes the anominate
is not going to get
better until you treat the
sacrum. So you have to use
your clinical judgment.
If one area is not
getting better, you need
to go and check the other
areas around it, see if
there's something holding
the initial area up.
Then you can move up and
treat the respiratory
diaphragm, maybe do some doming
of the diaphragm. Treating
the psoas might help
to release some of that
diaphragm because of the
interdigitation of the tendons
of the psoas in with the
cruce of the diaphragm.
You could also treat
rib 12 bilaterally.
That'll also have
an effect on the
diaphragm. You can use
BLT or muscle energy
or whatever you want
for that rib 12.
Then I like to jump up to
the thoracic outlet region
before i do the the thoracic
region um so you would
treat rib one bilaterally
use the still technique you
can use blt you can use
muscle energy if the patient
tolerates it i you know you
i wouldn't try hvla at this
point especially the methods
that you guys have been
taught already i i wouldn't
um i wouldn't necessarily
try that but uh but definitely
you want to treat that
that first rib. And you
also want to look at the
clavicles too and treat any
dysfunction in the clavicle.
Then maybe treat that
sternocleidomastoid.
Remember the
sternocleidomastoid attaches to
the first rib. So if
you're having trouble
treating the first rib,
you may need to treat
the sternocleidomastoid
first or vice versa.
In this case, we didn't
mention counterstrain
points, but you could look
for counterstrain points
in the sternocleidomastoid
and take it to a point
of ease and treat it using the
principles of counter-strain.
You could try some muscle
energy if the patient
will tolerate it. Now
you're getting into the
neck and that's where the
patient's having a lot
of pain, so you have to
be careful with that.
Also, you could try to use
some BLT techniques. Once
you learn how to treat the
cranium, you could also
treat the cranial base.
That'll help with the temporal
attachment at the mastoid
process. So if you're
the cranial base and the
thoracic out with the first
rib that might help to loosen
up that sternocleidomastoid
as well you also want
to treat t1 remember
t1 there's a there's like
c7 t1 and the first rib
there's that complex in there
and sometimes those areas
can be tough to treat so
you if the first rib's
not really moving you may
need to treat t1 first or
sometimes you treat the rib
first and then treat T1.
But to treat T1, you can
use BLT, muscle energy, FPR.
You can use a still technique.
Then you could treat, like I
said, you might
need to treat C7.
So you might have to go
treat that along with
when you're treating
the T1. And you could
treat that with still
technique or muscle
energy using the oculocervical
reflex or balance
ligamentous tension,
something like that.
Then to treat T5, you
can use still technique,
muscle energy. You can also use
HVLA if the patient
tolerates it.
Then go back up, treat
the OA, the AA, the
rest of the cervical
spine, and you can use
still technique. You
can use muscle energy.
You can use balanced
ligamentous tension.
And the little
asterisk at the bottom,
it just reinforces what
I've been saying. Sometimes
you need to treat one region
versus another in case
there's one dysfunction
is holding up another
dysfunction it's not all it's
not cookie cutter so there
are many different
approaches you could take the
way I've discussed here is
just one approach hopefully
you can tell that there
are different ways to treat
a patient we're talking
about still technique in
this lab so you can use
still technique if indicated
along with any other
indicated techniques to treat
your patient. As long as
it's not contraindicated
and you're comfortable and
the patient's comfortable,
you can use whatever
techniques you need to use.
Still technique is
indirect than direct, but
it's not as direct per se
as HVLA or muscle energy.
You're not, the patient's
not going to be,
like muscle energy patients
actually contracting
their their muscles still
technique is staying relaxed
so it's it's a gentle
technique and it's a great
technique to use whenever
you're treating a patient
these are some core
references you can use to
look up information
about the still technique
thank you